<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v2004 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by Ed Beach (Firaxis Games) -->
<!-- DLC Civilopedia Entries -->
<GameData>
	<Language_en_US>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_KOREA_SCENARIO_TITLE">
			<Text>The Samurai Invasion of Korea</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_KOREA_SCENARIO_DESC">
			<Text>The great warlord Toyotomi  Hideyoshi has unified Japan. To keep his Samurai busy, his eye now turns west to Korea. Will he be able to expand his empire? Or will Korea's Chinese ally arrive in time?</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_KOREA_SCENARIO_CIV5_DAWN_KOREA_TEXT">
			<Text>SCENARIO DESCRIPTION[NEWLINE]Blessings be upon you great one -- may the mandate of heaven guide you through these difficult times, for the winds of change are upon us, sweeping over East Asia. The victories of the great Japanese warlord Toyotomi Hideyoshi have at long last unified that island nation. Confident in Japan's new gunpowder weaponry, Hideyoshi now casts his eye to the west. Both the venerable Ming Dynasty in China and their ally the Choson Dynasty in Korea must be vigilant! And there is news of a new power taking shape to the north on the Manchurian Plain. Ready your soldiers, your horsemen, and your navies: all forms of weapons and technology must be brought to bear in the coming struggle for control of the lands surrounding the Yellow Sea![NEWLINE][NEWLINE]VICTORY CONDITIONS[NEWLINE]Japan or the Manchu win by conquering both Seoul and Beijing. China and Korea win by controlling all their original cities any time after the year 1600. If none of these conditions occur, the winner is the civ with the most points when the 100 turns are complete. Note that there are extra points earned for each enemy unit killed and for control of Seoul and Beijing.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]SPECIAL RULES[NEWLINE]Buy policies at the start to balance your happiness and gold. The only civ that can build new cities is the Manchu. Korea and China are an allied team that starts the game at war with Japan. Science has been turned off.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_KOREA_SCENARIO_CIV5_DAWN_JAPAN_TEXT">
			<Text>SCENARIO DESCRIPTION[NEWLINE]Blessings be upon you great one -- may the mandate of heaven guide you through these difficult times, for the winds of change are upon us, sweeping over East Asia. The victories of the great Japanese warlord Toyotomi Hideyoshi have at long last unified that island nation. Confident in Japan's new gunpowder weaponry, Hideyoshi now casts his eye to the west. Both the venerable Ming Dynasty in China and their ally the Choson Dynasty in Korea must be vigilant! And there is news of a new power taking shape to the north on the Manchurian Plain. Ready your soldiers, your horsemen, and your navies: all forms of weapons and technology must be brought to bear in the coming struggle for control of the lands surrounding the Yellow Sea![NEWLINE][NEWLINE]VICTORY CONDITIONS[NEWLINE]Japan or the Manchu win by conquering both Seoul and Beijing. China and Korea win by controlling all their original cities any time after the year 1600. If none of these conditions occur, the winner is the civ with the most points when the 100 turns are complete. Note that there are extra points earned for each enemy unit killed and for control of Seoul and Beijing.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]SPECIAL RULES[NEWLINE]Buy policies at the start to balance your happiness and gold. The only civ that can build new cities is the Manchu. Korea and China are an allied team that starts the game at war with Japan. Science has been turned off.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_KOREA_SCENARIO_CIV5_DAWN_CHINA_TEXT">
			<Text>SCENARIO DESCRIPTION[NEWLINE]Blessings be upon you great one -- may the mandate of heaven guide you through these difficult times, for the winds of change are upon us, sweeping over East Asia. The victories of the great Japanese warlord Toyotomi Hideyoshi have at long last unified that island nation. Confident in Japan's new gunpowder weaponry, Hideyoshi now casts his eye to the west. Both the venerable Ming Dynasty in China and their ally the Choson Dynasty in Korea must be vigilant! And there is news of a new power taking shape to the north on the Manchurian Plain. Ready your soldiers, your horsemen, and your navies: all forms of weapons and technology must be brought to bear in the coming struggle for control of the lands surrounding the Yellow Sea![NEWLINE][NEWLINE]VICTORY CONDITIONS[NEWLINE]Japan or the Manchu win by conquering both Seoul and Beijing. China and Korea win by controlling all their original cities any time after the year 1600. If none of these conditions occur, the winner is the civ with the most points when the 100 turns are complete. Note that there are extra points earned for each enemy unit killed and for control of Seoul and Beijing.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]SPECIAL RULES[NEWLINE]Buy policies at the start to balance your happiness and gold. The only civ that can build new cities is the Manchu. Korea and China are an allied team that starts the game at war with Japan. Science has been turned off.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_KOREA_SCENARIO_CIV5_DAWN_MONGOLIA_TEXT">
			<Text>SCENARIO DESCRIPTION[NEWLINE]Blessings be upon you great one -- may the mandate of heaven guide you through these difficult times, for the winds of change are upon us, sweeping over East Asia. The victories of the great Japanese warlord Toyotomi Hideyoshi have at long last unified that island nation. Confident in Japan's new gunpowder weaponry, Hideyoshi now casts his eye to the west. Both the venerable Ming Dynasty in China and their ally the Choson Dynasty in Korea must be vigilant! And there is news of a new power taking shape to the north on the Manchurian Plain. Ready your soldiers, your horsemen, and your navies: all forms of weapons and technology must be brought to bear in the coming struggle for control of the lands surrounding the Yellow Sea![NEWLINE][NEWLINE]VICTORY CONDITIONS[NEWLINE]Japan or the Manchu win by conquering both Seoul and Beijing. China and Korea win by controlling all their original cities any time after the year 1600. If none of these conditions occur, the winner is the civ with the most points when the 100 turns are complete. Note that there are extra points earned for each enemy unit killed and for control of Seoul and Beijing.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]SPECIAL RULES[NEWLINE]Buy policies at the start to balance your happiness and gold. The only civ that can build new cities is the Manchu. Korea and China are an allied team that starts the game at war with Japan. Science has been turned off.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_KOREA_SCENARIO_LEADER_GENGHIS_FIRSTGREETING_1">
			<Text>The proud and warlike Manchu people greet you. Treat us with respect and you may live to see another sunrise.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_KOREA_SCENARIO_BRIEFING">
			<Text>Briefing</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_KOREA_SCENARIO_TURNSREMAINING">
			<Text>Turns Left: {1_TurnsRemaining}[NEWLINE]</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_KOREA_SCENARIO_NEED_TO_CONQUER">
			<Text>Need to Conquer: </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_KOREA_SCENARIO_NEED_TO_REGAIN">
			<Text>Cities to Regain: {1_CitiesToRegain}</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_KOREA_SCENARIO_HOLD_CITIES">
			<Text>Must Hold Cities Until 1600</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_KOREA_SCENARIO_CIV_MONGOL_DESC">
			<Text>Manchu Empire</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_KOREA_SCENARIO_CIV_MONGOL_ADJECTIVE">
			<Text>Manchu</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_TRAIT_MANCHU_CONVERTS_LAND_BARBARIANS_SHORT">
			<Text>Eight Banners</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_TRAIT_MANCHU_CONVERTS_LAND_BARBARIANS">
			<Text>Upon destroying a Barbarian encampment, the former camp guard joins your side. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_TRAIT_KOREA_RIGHTEOUS_ARMY_SHORT">
			<Text>Righteous Army</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_TRAIT_KOREA_RIGHTEOUS_ARMY">
			<Text>Never eliminated from the game, even when they lose their last city. Periodically receive free units to retake their captured cities. These include Turtle Ships and Archers enhanced with the ability to withdraw before facing a melee attack.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_KOREA_SCENARIO_UNIT_HELP_SETTLER">
			<Text>Founds new Cities to expand your empire. Each new city will start with a Monument, Granary, and Market.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE][ICON_FOOD] Growth of the City is stopped while this Unit is being built.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_KOREA_SCENARIO_CIV5_ANTIQUITY_SETTLER_TEXT">
			<Text>The tribal Jurchen clans, predecessors to the Manchu Dynasty and its people, inhabited the region known as Manchuria, now in present-day northern China. Before the rise of the Manchu Dynasty in the 17th century, the Jurchen briefly united under the banner of the Jin Dynasty in the 12th century. Throughout their history, the Jurchen were known as skilled hunters and equestrians alike, priding themselves on the talents of their cavalry.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_KOREA_SCENARIO_NO_ACTION_SETTLER_SIZE_LIMIT_HARDCODED">
			<Text>[NEWLINE]Clans may only be built in Cities with at least 2 [ICON_CITIZEN] Citizens.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_KOREA_SCENARIO_CIV5_MONGOLIA_KESHIK_HEADING">
			<Text>Manchu Banner Cavalry</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_KOREA_SCENARIO_CIV5_MONGOLIA_KESHIK_TEXT">
			<Text>The Eight Banners, created by Manchu founder Nurhaci in the early 17th century, was a system of administration intended to organize the dynasty's military. Initially created to divide the soldiers into different companies, the banner system later came to utilize ethnically-segregated units, as the Manchu military was made up of Manchu, Han, and Mongol troops who typically didn't intermingle. The Manchu and Mongol banner companies were ideal cavalrymen, their long history of nomadic equestrianism breeding formidable mounted troops.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_KOREA_SCENARIO_CIV5_MONGOLIA_KESHIK_HELP">
			<Text>This Manchu Unique Unit replaces the standard Knight. It possesses a strong ranged attack, increased movement rate, and earns promotions at a double rate. Unit battles also contribute double the amount of points towards earning a Great General.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_KOREA_SCENARIO_CIV5_MONGOLIA_KESHIK_INFO">
			<Text>Banner Cavalry is a Manchu Unique Unit, available in the Medieval Era.  This replacement for the standard Knight moves at an increased rate, earns promotions at a double rate, and contributes twice the amount of points towards earning Great Generals. Banner Cavalry can also attack its enemies from afar, using its powerful ranged attack.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_KOREA_SCENARIO_CIV5_MONGOLIA_KESHIK_STRATEGY">
			<Text>Banner Cavalry is a unique replacement for the Knight, available to the Manchu starting in the Medieval Era.  Banner Cavalry possess a strong ranged attack and an increased movement rate (5 points total), allowing it to perform hit and run attacks remarkably effectively.  If this wasn't enough, Banner Cavalry also acquires promotions at double the rate of other units, and contributes twice the amount of points towards earning Great Generals.  These mounted warriors singlehandedly afford the Manchu control of the open plains.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_KOREA_SCENARIO_CIV_MANCHURIA_HEADING_1">
			<Text>History</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_KOREA_SCENARIO_CIV_MANCHURIA_TEXT_1">
			<Text>The Manchu Dynasty of China, also known as the Qing Dynasty, traces its foundations to the Jurchen tribes who inhabited the region historically known as Manchuria. First established in the 17th century by the Jurchen tribal leader Nurhaci, the Manchu under Nurhaci embarked on a campaign of expansion and conquest against the powerful Ming Dynasty. Eventually overthrowing the Ming and laying claim to vast swaths of territory, the Manchu Dynasty ruled China for nearly 300 years, and was the last dynasty of China before the formation of the People's Republic.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_KOREA_SCENARIO_LEADER_NURHACI_NAME">
			<Text>Nurhaci of the Jurchen</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_KOREA_SCENARIO_LEADER_NURHACI_SUBTITLE">
			<Text>Khan of the Later Jin Dynasty</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_KOREA_SCENARIO_LEADER_NURHACI_LIVED">
			<Text>1558 - 1626 AD</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_KOREA_SCENARIO_LEADER_NURHACI_HEADING_1">
			<Text>History</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_KOREA_SCENARIO_LEADER_NURHACI_TEXT_1">
			<Text>Esteemed chieftain Nurhaci of the Jurchen is credited with uniting the nomadic Jurchen tribes of China and creating the foundations of the Manchu Dynasty. Leading during the latter half of the 16th century, Nurhaci was the first Khan of the Jin Dynasty, which later came to be known as the Qing or Manchu Dynasty following his death. During his reign, Nurhaci set his people on a quest to overtake the rival Ming Dynasty of China and eventually the Choson Dynasty of Korea. Nurhaci is notably credited with the creation of the Eight Banners, an organizational system for his military that divided the troops into banner companies of varying size.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_KOREA_SCENARIO_BUILDING_PAPER_MAKER_STRATEGY">
			<Text>The Paper Maker is the Chinese unique building, replacing the Bank. The Paper Maker increases the city's intake of gold.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_KOREA_SCENARIO_BUILDING_PAPER_MAKER_HELP">
			<Text>+4[ICON_GOLD] Gold.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_KOREA_SCENARIO_IMPROVEMENT_WAJO">
			<Text>Wajo</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_KOREA_SCENARIO_BUILD_WAJO">
			<Text>Construct a [LINK=IMPROVEMENT_WAJO]Wajo[\LINK]</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_KOREA_SCENARIO_BUILD_WAJO_REC">
			<Text>It will improve the [ICON_STRENGTH] Defense of any military unit stationed in this tile.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_KOREA_SCENARIO_BUILD_WAJO_HELP">
			<Text>+50% [ICON_STRENGTH] Defensive Strength for any Unit stationed in this Tile. Can only be built by Japan and must be built on a Coast tile. Any enemy unit which ends its turn next to the Wajo takes 2 damage.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_CIV5_IMPROVEMENTS_WAJO_HELP">
			<Text>The Wajo is a Japanese unique improvement, replacing Forts in this scenario. It must be built on coastal tiles. It improves the Defensive Strength of any Unit stationed here by 50% and any enemy unit ending its turn next to the Wajo takes 2 damage.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_CIV5_IMPROVEMENTS_WAJO_TEXT">
			<Text>A Wajo is a special improvement that doesn't increase a hex's productivity or provide access to a resource. Instead, a Wajo inflicts 2 damage on enemy units that end their turn adjacent and it improves a hex's defensive bonus by 50% for units stationed in that hex. However, Wajos do not provide a defensive bonus to units in enemy territory.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]During the Japanese invasions of Korea known as the Imjin War, the Japanese military constructed numerous hastily built castles, known as Wajo, along the coastline. Used as outposts and garrisons primarily along the southern coast of Korea, the military typically built artificial hills or plateaus upon which they placed wooden walls, towers and internal structures that closely matched the characteristic style of traditional Japanese castles. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_KOREA_SCENARIO_VP_FUTURE_TECH">
			<Text>Combat Kills</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_KOREA_SCENARIO_VP_TECH">
			<Text>Seoul and Beijing</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_KOREA_SCENARIO_DIPLO_MY_SCORE_FUTURE_TECH">
			<Text>{1_Num} from Combat Kills</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_KOREA_SCENARIO_DIPLO_MY_SCORE_TECH">
			<Text>{1_Num} from Seoul and Beijing</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_PROMOTION_GUERILLA_WITHDRAW">
			<Text>Guerilla Withdraw Before Melee</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_PROMOTION_GUERILLA_WITHDRAW_HELP">
			<Text>Unit will withdraw when faced with melee attack. Chance of withdrawal decreased against fast enemy units or if there are limited open tiles behind the unit.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_KOREA_SCENARIO_BUILDING_PORCELAIN_TOWER_STRATEGY">
			<Text>The Porcelain Tower increases the speed of production of melee and naval units.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_KOREA_SCENARIO_WONDER_PORCELAIN_TOWER_HELP">
			<Text>+15% [ICON_PRODUCTION] Production when building Melee or Naval Units.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_KOREA_SCENARIO_GUERILLAS_SPAWNED">
			<Text>Korea has received new guerilla units because of their Righteous Army trait.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_KOREA_SCENARIO_TECH_SPREAD">
			<Text>Your defeat of this {1_UnitName} has unlocked the {2_TechName} technology!  You may now build {3_UnitName} in your cities.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_KOREA_SCENARIO_MANCHU_DOW">
			<Text>The newly united Manchu tribes have seen how China and Korea have been weakened by the ongoing war with Japan.  They take this opportunity to declare war!</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_KOREA_SCENARIO_NINGXIA_REBELLION_OVER">
			<Text>The Chinese army has defeated a rebellion in the western Ningxia province. New Chinese reinforcements are on the way.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_KOREA_SCENARIO_WAJO_REINFORCEMENTS">
			<Text>Japanese reinforcements have landed on the Wajo fortifications they have constructed on the Korean peninsula.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_KOREA_SCENARIO_JAPANESE_REINFORCEMENTS">
			<Text>Japanese reinforcements have landed on the Korean peninsula.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_KOREA_SCENARIO_EXTRA_MANCHU_UNITS">
			<Text>An additonal Jurchen tribe has heard of the growing Manchu strength and joined the Manchu cause.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_KOREA_SCENARIO_POLICY_COLLECTIVE_RULE_HELP">
			<Text>[COLOR_POSITIVE_TEXT]Collective Rule[ENDCOLOR][NEWLINE][ICON_GOLD] Gold cost of purchasing units reduced by 33%.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_KOREA_SCENARIO_MAP_TITLE">
			<Text>East Asia</Text>
		</Row>
	</Language_en_US>
</GameData>
