<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v2004 rel. 2 U (http://www.xmlspy.com) by Ed Beach (Firaxis Games) -->
<!-- DLC Civilopedia Entries -->
<GameData>
	<Language_en_US>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_CIV5_DAWN_KOREA_TEXT">
			<Text>Greetings to you, exalted King Sejong the Great, servant to the people and protector of the Choson Dynasty. Your glorious vision of prosperity and overwhelming benevolence towards the common man made you the most beloved of all Korean kings. From the earliest days of your reign, the efforts you took to provide a fair and just society for all were surpassed only by the technological advancements spurred onwards by your unquenched thirst for knowledge. Guided by your wisdom, the scholars of the Jade Hall developed Korea's first written language, Hangul, bringing the light of literature and science to the masses after centuries of literary darkness.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Honorable Sejong, once more the people look to you for guidance! Will you rise to the occasion, bringing harmony and understanding to the people? Can you once again advance your kingdom's standing to such wondrous heights? Can you build a civilization that stands the test of time?

      </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_CIV5_KOREA_TITLE">
			<Text>Korea</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_CIV5_KOREA_HEADING_1">
			<Text>History</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_CIV5_KOREA_HEADING_2">
			<Text>Climate and Terrain</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_CIV5_KOREA_HEADING_3">
			<Text>Pre-History and the Old Kingdom</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_CIV5_KOREA_HEADING_4">
			<Text>Rise of the Three</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_CIV5_KOREA_HEADING_5">
			<Text>Transforming Kingdoms</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_CIV5_KOREA_HEADING_6">
			<Text>Choson Dynasty</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_CIV5_KOREA_HEADING_7">
			<Text>Korean Empire</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_CIV5_KOREA_HEADING_8">
			<Text>Japanese Occupation</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_CIV5_KOREA_HEADING_9">
			<Text>Korean War</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_CIV5_KOREA_HEADING_10">
			<Text>Division of Korea</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_CIV5_KOREA_HEADING_11">
			<Text>Modern Korea</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_CIV5_KOREA_STATBOX">
			<Text>[NEWLINE]        Leader: SEJONG[NEWLINE]        Unique Unit: Tercio[NEWLINE]        Unique Unit: Conquistador[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_CIV5_KOREA_TEXT_1">
			<Text>The Korean peninsula, known today for its divided republics of North and South Korea, has been home to numerous kingdoms over the ages, some virtuous, some steeped in infamy. At times rivaling its powerful neighboring states of China and Japan, Korea was united under the rule of the Choson Dynasty for over 500 years. The turmoil of the Japanese occupation in the early 20th century, followed by the Korean War in 1950, would shatter this once sacred unity. From this strife, South Korea has emerged as a nation of increasing economic and cultural significance on a global scale. In contrast, the oppressive regime controlling the reclusive North Korean state is frequently the subject of international condemnation for its handling of human rights and diplomatic relations.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_CIV5_KOREA_TEXT_2">
			<Text>Situated between the East Sea and the Yellow Sea, the Korean Peninsula shares its northern border with China, and to a lesser extent Russia, separated respectively by the Amnok and Tumen rivers.  Although Korea features a diverse geography, the country is primarily mountainous, the highest peak being Baekdu Mountain at 9,003 ft (2,744m). Like its neighbors, Korea is affected by the East Asian Monsoon each summer, bringing the possibility of intense rainfall and oppressive humidity to much of the region. The winter months can also be quite harsh, with subzero temperatures not uncommon, particularly in the north.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_CIV5_KOREA_TEXT_3">
			<Text>From at least the Middle Paleolithic era, Korea was inhabited by humans living in caves or under rock outcroppings near the sea. Over the course of several thousand years, primitive communities would form, primarily as these gatherers became more adept at hunting. Of the numerous early communities found throughout the peninsula, one in particular would rise to prominence and become the foundation for all of the Korean kingdoms to come - "Ko Choson," also known as "Old Choson."[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Old Choson was founded in approximately 2000 BC by the legendary figure Tan'gun Wanggom, whose father is said to have descended from the heavens.  Some modern historians believe the name "Tan'gun Wanggom" may have actually been a title given to early authority figures, representing both a political and religious figure within the community.  Whether guided by the hand of a single leader, or a number of early rulers, Old Choson would become the most advanced of the early Korean tribal kingdoms throughout the advent of the Iron Age in the 4th century BC.
</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_CIV5_KOREA_TEXT_4">
			<Text>For most of the 1st millennium AD, Korea was divided by the rule of three distinct monarchies. The "Three Kingdoms of Korea" -- Koguryo, Paekche, and Silla -- each controlled a segment of the peninsula, with Koguryo being the largest and, for a time, the most powerful. However, diplomatic relations would prove to be the undoing of the Koguryo, as its southernmost rival, Silla, negotiated an alliance with the Tang Dynasty of China. This alliance would bring great strength to Silla, allowing them to conquer both the Paekche and the Koguryo by 668, leaving the Silla with uncontested control of most of the Korean Peninsula. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_CIV5_KOREA_TEXT_5">
			<Text>Having conquered the kingdoms of Koguryo and Paekche, the new "Unified Silla," often referred to as the "Later Silla," would continue to control the peninsula for several hundred years. As is often the case after such a long period of uninterrupted dominion, the authority of the king began to come into question around the 9th century AD. The "bone-rank system," a sort of hereditary segregation based on a person's blood ties to the king, had maintained the balance of power between the king and the aristocratic nobility for some time. However, this system would ultimately contribute to the downfall of the Silla, as the nobility they desperately relied on for taxation and management grew tired of the caste system that limited their role in governance.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]In the end, continuous internal strife would lead to the kingdom's submission to the emerging Koryo Dynasty by 935. The Koryo would maintain a sovereign kingdom within Korea, despite pressure from the Mongol Yuan Dynasty of China, until 1392.
</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_CIV5_KOREA_TEXT_6">
			<Text>The Choson Dynasty, widely regarded as the most notable kingdom in Korea's history, was founded by the rebellious Koryo Commander Yi Song-gye in 1392. Ordered to invade the neighboring Chinese province of Liaotung (a pre-emptive strike against the Chinese Ming Dynasty), Yi instead seized the opportunity to control Korea himself, leading his army into the Koryo capital and dethroning the king in a military coup. Forming his own dynasty and renaming himself King Taejo of Choson, named for the ancient Choson kingdom, Taejo would create the first unified Korean dynasty in the country's history.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]The most revered of the Choson leaders, King Sejong the Great, ruled from 1418 until his death in 1450. Sejong's policies paved the way for vast strides in the arts and sciences during his reign, including the publication of the Korean written language, "Hangul." It was also during this period that Korean Confucianism, its roots established during the preceding Koryo dynasty, would take hold over Korea. Neo-Confucianism, known as "Seongnihak," would become the primary school of thought for scholars across the peninsula. These Confucian values, emphasizing morality and self-improvement, became the basis for many of the values held sacred by Korean society today.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]The Choson Dynasty would be ruled by 27 distinct monarchs during its 500-year rule, ending in 1897. During the waning years of the dynasty, Korea underwent a period of isolationism, limiting contact with the surrounding nations in an effort to blunt outside influence. Having long been the subject of Chinese and Japanese influence, many historians believe that it was during this period, when Korea became known as the "Hermit Kingdom," that the first hints of a modern Korean national identity began to take shape. 
</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_CIV5_KOREA_TEXT_7">
			<Text>The First Sino-Japanese war, fought between China and Japan across large swaths of the Korean peninsula beginning in 1894, would provide the first glimpse of Japan's emerging strength in East Asia. Having long been the subject of Chinese influence and fearful of the emerging power demonstrated by Japan, the Choson leadership saw fit to declare the creation of the Korean Empire in 1897. Hoping to assert Korea's independence from both China and Japan, these aspirations would be short lived. Japan quickly moved to assert control over Korea after defeating much of the Chinese Qing Dynasty's forces.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_CIV5_KOREA_TEXT_8">
			<Text>The Japan-Korea Treaty of 1910 (which Korean historians to this day claim was only signed under extreme duress) would effectively annex the whole of Korea to Japan. Despite an active resistance movement among the Korean people from the early stages of the occupation, Japan maintained control over the nation for nearly 35 years. The "Provisional Government of the Republic of Korea," based in Shanghai, China, would serve as the Korean government- in-exile throughout the occupation.  Japan's hold over Korea finally came to an end on September 2, 1945 following Japan's defeat in World War II. Today, many Koreans still harbor a strong resentment towards Japan for this dark period in their history.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_CIV5_KOREA_TEXT_9">
			<Text>The Korean War, the great conflict that divided the Korean Peninsula as it stands today, arose from the vacuum of power following Japan's defeat in World War II. The 38th Parallel, a dividing line agreed upon by the United States and the Soviet Union, was expected to mark a temporary administrative split between the countries. In 1948, North Korea would form a communist government led by Kim II-Sung, while South Korea elected its first president, Syngman Rhee, via national elections. Both leaders insisted the Korean people should be united under one rule, but each expected the unification to occur under their own political system.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]In June of 1950, North Korea invaded the South, aided by Soviet military equipment from World War II. Shortly thereafter, the United Nations issued a resolution condemning the invasion and recommending military intervention by its member states. At the time, the United States considered the spread of Communism to be a direct result of Soviet influence, and responded as the primary military force aiding South Korea.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Although North Korea captured much of the southern territory early in the war, the arrival of American forces under the leadership of General MacArthur soon countered those gains. Eventually regaining South Korea's territory up to the 38th Parallel, the American and South Korean forces would fight the North to an eventual stalemate.  Negotiations for an armistice, which would serve to end the fighting - but not officially end the war - began in 1951 and would continue for several years. The armistice agreement was finally signed by the Democratic People's Republic of Korea (North) and the Republic of Korea (South) under the guidance of the United Nations in 1953.
</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_CIV5_KOREA_TEXT_10">
			<Text>Officially, the armistice agreement signed by the Korean republics only stipulated an end to the fighting, meaning the two are theoretically still at war. Today, the Demilitarized Zone (DMZ) dividing them is the most heavily fortified border on earth, with both sides vigilantly observing the other. Over the years, a number of incidental incursions and other violations of the armistice have occurred, primarily antagonistic actions by the North Korean regime. Despite these incidents, the delicate cease fire has remained in effect for over 50 years.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_CIV5_KOREA_TEXT_11">
			<Text>Today, South Korea has become a world leader in science and technological development, and is recognized as one of the "Four Asian Tigers," a group of four highly developed industrialized economies in Asia (the other three being Hong Kong, Singapore, and Taiwan). Home to a well-educated and highly-skilled work force, South Korea has a strong culture of technological adoption, boasting some of the fastest residential internet connections available, and is home to industry leaders Samsung and LG, two of the largest mobile phone manufacturers in the world.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Conversely, the secretive government of North Korea has struggled to provide the necessities of daily life to its people, who are known to suffer through famine and poverty under the Communist regime. Isolated from public scrutiny, what little we know of North Korea comes from defectors who have managed to escape or from the rarely allowed visit by foreign journalists. Frequently sanctioned for developing weapons programs deemed dangerous by the international community, North Korea has a limited economy and is supported by constant aid from the People's Republic of China and humanitarian efforts initiated by the United Nations member states. 
</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_CIV5_KOREA_FACTOID_HEADING">
			<Text>Korea Factoids</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_CIV5_KOREA_FACTOID_TEXT">
			<Text>South Korea is famous for its gaming culture, particularly a love affair with the classic Blizzard title "Starcraft". Professional matches and tournaments receive widespread media attention throughout the country, including broadcasts on several television networks.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]The Chinese characters for Choson were often translated into English as "Morning Calm," which later evolved into the nickname "The Land of the Morning Calm," referring to all of Korea.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Kimchi, the widely recognized dish native to Korea, generally accompanies every meal in Korean cuisine. Typically made from fermented cabbage, radish, scallions, or cucumbers, there are literally hundreds of unique recipes and varieties of Kimchi available today.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]The national sport of South Korea, Tae Kwon Do, is attributed to the original nine "Kwans," or schools of Tae Kwon Do, that developed after the end of the Japanese occupation of Korea. The sport itself is believed to have originated with the traditional Korean martial art known as "Taekkyeon."
</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_CIV5_SEJONG_LIVED">
			<Text>1397 - 1450 AD</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_CIV5_SEJONG_NAME">
			<Text>Sejong the Great</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_CIV5_SEJONG_SUBTITLE">
			<Text>Leader of Korea</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_CIV5_SEJONG_TITLES_1">
			<Text>King of the Choson Dynasty</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_CIV5_SEJONG_HEADING_1">
			<Text>History</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_CIV5_SEJONG_HEADING_2">
			<Text>Early Life</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_CIV5_SEJONG_HEADING_3">
			<Text>Language, Literature, and Science</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_CIV5_SEJONG_HEADING_4">
			<Text>The Magnanimous Leader</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_CIV5_SEJONG_HEADING_5">
			<Text>Law and the Criminal Justice System</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_CIV5_SEJONG_HEADING_6">
			<Text>Military Advancements</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_CIV5_SEJONG_HEADING_7">
			<Text>Judgment of History</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_CIV5_SEJONG_TEXT_1">
			<Text>Sejong Daewang, known to history as "Sejong the Great," was the fourth king of the Choson Dynasty of Korea, ruling from 1418 until his death in 1450. Considered by many to be the greatest king in Korean history, Sejong is known for his remarkable appreciation and respect for human life, adopting numerous civic and social policies to improve the well-being of his people. Sejong also encouraged advances in science and technology and is credited with the creation of the Korean written language, Hunminjeongeum, known today as "Hangul."  </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_CIV5_SEJONG_TEXT_2">
			<Text>Born on May 7th, 1397, Sejong was the third son of King Taejong of the Choson Dynasty. Said to have been an exceptional student and avid reader at an early age, Sejong was named Crown Prince at age 16. At age 21, Sejong ascended to the throne, and his impact on Korean life and the kingdom's political structure would be immediate.
      </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_CIV5_SEJONG_TEXT_3">
			<Text>Sejong is perhaps most famously known for his introduction of the Korean written language, Hangul.  The "Chiphyonjon," or "Hall of Worthies," established in 1420, was a collective of noted scholars selected by the king himself. Initially created as an institute of research, the Chiphyonjon would eventually be tasked with the creation of a Korean alphabet to aid the common people in their understanding of the Korean language.  Until this time, Korea had relied on the Chinese "Hanja" script, incorporated into the Korean dialect, for all written works. However, this script was not widely understood by the masses, and Sejong sought to change this trend of illiteracy.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Originally known as "Hunminjeongeum," literally meaning "The Correct Sounds for the Instruction of the People," this native Korean script would usher in a new era of literacy and understanding for the common citizens of Korea. First published in 1446, it would be several years before the new script found wide acceptance. To this day, October 9th, the original date of publication, is celebrated as "Hangul Day" throughout South Korea. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_CIV5_SEJONG_TEXT_4">
			<Text>Sejong's legacy is one of great benevolence, led by his strong belief that all people were worthy of his respect, not only the subjects within his kingdom, but even the so-called "barbarian tribes" scattered throughout Asia. The standard by which he measured his own success as a leader was the happiness and prosperity of his people, their welfare being his highest priority. As king, Sejong would provide surplus food supplies to the poor and elderly, and frequently abolished taxes on farmers and occasionally entire provinces that had experienced hardships due to weather or poor crop yields. Sejong was also known for inviting the elderly to banquets in their honor, regardless of the rank or social status of those attending. </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_CIV5_SEJONG_TEXT_5">
			<Text>Sejong mandated a number of improvements to the Korean justice system in order to provide fair trials and reasonable punishments for the convicted. Sejong believed it was unjust to hold citizens accountable for violating the law without ensuring they were provided a means to understand the laws they had broken. Despite the reluctance of his ministers, Sejong ordered the entirety of the Korean legal code be put on public display, for all to see.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Sejong also opposed the death penalty, and informed judges that it was not to be used unless absolutely necessary. His implementation of "The Law of Three Appeals" allowed the accused up to three appeals to the king, ensuring they were provided with an opportunity to speak on their own behalf.
      </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_CIV5_SEJONG_TEXT_6">
			<Text>Under Sejong, Korea began the development of various early gunpowder weapons, most famously the "Hwach'a," or "Fire Vehicle." Specifically designed as an anti-infantry weapon, the Hwach'a was a wheeled platform capable of launching dozens of gunpowder-propelled arrows across the battlefield. Although limited in use during Sejong's time, the Hwach'a would become a crucial defensive weapon throughout the Korean peninsula for centuries to come. During the Battle of Haengju in 1593, three thousand Korean soldiers repelled an invading Japanese force of over 30,000 by successfully utilizing the Hwach'a, inflicting over 10,000 casualities.
      </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_CIV5_SEJONG_TEXT_7">
			<Text>In old age, Sejong is said to have continued his involvement in daily routines and government affairs, despite going blind and developing diabetes, which would be the eventual cause of his death on May 18, 1450. Sejong is remembered in history for his wise, noble, and compassionate leadership that spurred amazing advances in science and technology, and led to a revolution in the cultural development of the Korean people for centuries to come.
      </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_CIV5_SEJONG_FACTOID_HEADING">
			<Text>Sejong Factoids</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_CIV5_SEJONG_FACTOID_TEXT">
			<Text>The Republic of Korea Navy employs a class of guided missile destroyers known as "King Sejong the Great", developed under the "Korean Destroyer eXperimental (KDX)" program.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]The likeness of King Sejong the Great appears in Korean currency on the 10,000 Won note.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]A Korean television drama produced in 2008, entitled "Daewang Sejong," chronicled the life of Sejong the Great during his reign.[NEWLINE][NEWLINE]Designated a UNESCO World Heritage site in 2009, King Sejong's tomb, known as Yeongneung, is located in Gyeonggi-do in present-day South Korea.
      </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_CIV5_KOREA_TURTLESHIP_TEXT">
			<Text>These large, armored warships of the Choson dynasty played a crucial role in the defense of Korea during the Japanese invasions of the 16th century. Typically crewed by an equal compliment of soldiers and oarsmen, the Turtle Ship provided an aggressive close-assault ship for the Korean navy. Designed to strike fear in the enemy, each Turtle Ship featured a carved dragon figurehead on its bow, said to have emitted a cloud of sulfurous fumes to disguise the vessel's approach.  Unlike the familiar designs used by sailing ships of the period, the Turtle Ship had no upper deck. The top level of the ship was covered in iron spikes to prevent boarding, with the oarsmen and soldiers segregated onto separate decks below. Armed with up to two dozen cannons and other small projectile weapons, the Turtle Ship was a dangerous foe for the unprepared navies of Korea's enemies.
      </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_CIV5_KOREA_TURTLESHIP_HELP">
			<Text>Heavily-armored naval unit of the Renaissance Era that is extremely difficult to kill. However Turtle Ships cannot enter deep ocean hexes outside of the city borders. Only Korea may build it. Replaces the Caravel.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_CIV5_KOREA_TURTLESHIP_STRATEGY">
			<Text>The Turtle Ship is a Korean unique unit. This unit replaces the Caravel. The Turtle Ship has a more powerful attack than the Caravel, and is extremely difficult to destroy.  However it may not enter deep ocean hexes outside of the city borders.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_CIV5_KOREA_HWACHA_TEXT">
			<Text>The Hwach'a, legendary Korean anti-infantry weapon, was a unique innovation in the development of early gunpowder-based weaponry. Created during the 15th century under the supervision of King Sejong the Great, the Hwach'a consisted of a large two-wheeled cart carrying a type of "honeycomb" housing, not unlike a modern missile battery, capable of storing hundreds of gunpowder-propelled arrows. The light-weight of these early rockets, known as "Singijeon," provided the Hwach'a with a notable advantage, allowing excellent maneuverability compared to a traditional cannon. The Hwach'a would prove to be a formidable weapon for the defense of the Korean Peninsula during the Japanese invasions of the 16th century.
      </Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_CIV5_KOREA_HWACHA_HELP">
			<Text>Anti-personnel rocket unit of the Medieval Era. Strong against land units, but weak against cities. Only Korea may build it. Replaces the Trebuchet.</Text>
		</Row>
		<Row Tag="TXT_KEY_CIV5_KOREA_HWACHA_STRATEGY">
			<Text>The Hwach'a is extremely effective against enemy land units. It is slow and vulnerable to enemy melee attack; it always should be supported by other units when it's in the field. The Hwach'a must "set up" (1 Movement Point) before attacking.</Text>
		</Row>
	</Language_en_US>
</GameData>
